As a first example,
كمثال أول،
let's apply this new idea of notation to something you've used before.
دعونا نطبق هذه الفكرة الجديدة للتدوين على شيء استخدمته من قبل.
Spreadsheets. Spreadsheets are a common way we hold data in the real world.
جداول البيانات. تعد جداول البيانات طريقة شائعة نمتلك بها البيانات في العالم الحقيقي.
In our spreadsheet, we have rows and columns.
في جدول البيانات الخاص بنا، لدينا صفوف وأعمدة.
To better understand how we use spreadsheets to hold data,
للحصول على فهم أفضل لكيفية استخدامنا لجداول البيانات لاحتواء البيانات،
let's work through an example.
دعونا نعمل من خلال مثال.
Before even collecting data,
قبل جمع البيانات،
we usually start with a question or many questions.
نبدأ عادةً بطرح سؤال أو أسئلة كثيرة.
Consider I run a small blog about my
فكر في تشغيل مدونة صغيرة عن
best and worst adventures with the dogs at the coffee shop.
أفضل وأسوأ مغامرات مع الكلاب في المقهى.
Which also sells trinkets related to those adventures.
التي تبيع أيضا الحلي المتعلقة بهذه المغامرات.
Everything from fetch toys to leashes,
كل شيء بدءًا من جلب اللعب إلى المقاود،
to doggie bags, and everything in between.
إلى أكياس الكلب، وكل شيء بينهما.
Questions I might have are: How many people visit my site?
الأسئلة التي قد تكون لدينا هي: كم شخص يزور موقعي؟
Or how much time do visitors spend on my site?
أو كم من الوقت يقضيه الزوار على موقعي؟
Are there differences in traffic,
هل هناك اختلافات في الحركة،
depending on the day of the week?
اعتمادًا على يوم الأسبوع؟
How many visitors purchase an item through the blog?
كم عدد الزوار الذين يشترون عنصرًا من خلال المدونة؟
In order to answer these questions,
للإجابة عن هذه الأسئلة،
say we keep track of the date of the visit,
لنفترض أننا نتتبع تاريخ الزيارة،
the day of the week of the visit,
وأيام الأسبوع من الزيارة،
the amount of time spent on the site,
ومقدار الوقت المستغرق على الموقع،
and whether or not an individual buys an item.
وما إذا كان الفرد يشتري عنصرًا أم لا.
We can think of each of these as a column.
يمكننا أن نفكر في كل من هذه كعمود.
A column in our dataset is associated with a random variable.
يرتبط عمود في مجموعة البيانات بمتغير عشوائي.
Explaining what a random variable is in English is complicated.
تفسير المتغير العشوائي في اللغة الإنجليزية أمر معقد.
But in notation, it's simple.
لكن بالتدوين، يصبح الأمر بسيطًا.
In English, a random variable is a placeholder for the possible values of some process.
في اللغة الإنجليزية، المتغير العشوائي هو عنصر نائب للقيم المحتملة لبعض العمليات.
In notation, it's X.
في التدوين، هو X.
For our website, the date of the visit,
لموقع الويب الخاص بنا، تاريخ الزيارة
the day of the week of the visit,
وأيام الأسبوع من الزيارة،
the amount of time spent on the site,
ومقدار الوقت المستغرق على الموقع،
and whether or not an individual buys an item are all variables.
وما إذا كان الفرد يشتري عنصرًا أم تعد جميعها متغيرات.
Let's say we have a visitor on Thursday, June 15.
لنفترض أن لدينا زائر يوم الخميس، 15 يونيو.
The visitor stays on our site for five minutes and doesn't buy an item.
يظل الزائر على موقعنا لمدة خمس دقائق ولا يشتري سلعة.
Then a second visitor,
ثم يزور أحد الزائرين
visits the site on the exact same day for 10 minutes and they do buy an item.
الموقع في اليوم نفسه بالضبط لمدة 10 دقائق ويقوم بشراء أحد العناصر.
Notice how each of these individuals has been added to our spreadsheet.
لاحظ كيف تمت إضافة كل من هؤلاء الأفراد إلى جدول البيانات.
We might have many more visitors,
قد يكون لدينا المزيد من الزوار،
and we could update our spreadsheet accordingly.
ويمكننا تحديث جدول البيانات وفقًا لذلك.
When using spreadsheets, we frequently
عند استخدام جداول البيانات، نقوم بشكل متكرر
analyze a full column to answer our questions of interest.
بتحليل عمود كامل للإجابة على الأسئلة التي تهمنا.
For example, to answer the question of how much time do visitors spend on our site?
على سبيل المثال، للإجابة على السؤال عن مقدار الوقت الذي يقضيه الزوار على موقعنا؟
We need to look at this column.
نحتاج إلى النظر في هذا العمود.
To answer the question of,
للإجابة على سؤال،
Are there differences in traffic,
هل هناك اختلافات في الحركة،
depending on the day of the week?
اعتمادًا على يوم الأسبوع؟
We need to look at this column.
نحتاج إلى النظر في هذا العمود.
And to answer the question of,
وللإجابة على سؤال،
How many purchases occur through our blog?
كم عدد المشتريات التي تتم من خلال مدونتنا؟
We need to look at this column.
نحتاج إلى النظر في هذا العمود.
Mathematically, we usually consider a random variable or column using a capital letter.
من الناحية الرياضية، عادةً ما نفكر في متغير عشوائي أو عمود عشوائي باستخدام حرف كبير.
Commonly, we use the capital letter X,
عادة، نستخدم الحرف الكبير X،
but we can just as easily use Y,
لكن يمكننا بسهولة استخدام Y،
Z or any other capital letter.
أو Z أو أي حرف كبير آخر.
We might say, consider the random variable X,
قد نقول، نفكر في المتغير العشوائي X،
which signifies the amount of time an individual spends on our website.
الذي يشير إلى مقدار الوقت الذي يقضيه الفرد على موقعنا.
Therefore, X relates to this entire column.
لذلك، يتعلق X بهذا العمود بأكمله.
Consider we also have a random variable Y,
لنفترض أيضًا أن لدينا متغيرًا عشوائيًا Y،
which signifies whether or not an individual purchases an item from the website,
يشير إلى ما إذا كان الفرد يشتري عنصرًا من موقع الويب،
so Y relates to this entire column.
لذلك يرتبط Y بهذا العمود بأكمله.